Hey, I'm Andrea Dudik, realtor and
associate broker here in the central
Texas area. I've helped dozens of
families relocate to the Temple Belton
area. And a question I frequently get
asked is, is Belton, Texas really a
great place to live? Well, today we'll
be going over the pros, cons, and
everything in between so you can really
make that decision for yourself.
[Music]
Hey, and welcome back to Living in
Central Texas. If you're new to this
channel, don't forget to like,
subscribe, and click the bell
notification so that you can stay up
to-date on all things real estate here
in Central Texas.
This video is going to be a very
comprehensive and I think just very
straightforward
um example of all of the great reasons
to live here and maybe some things you
should really consider. Um as you may or
may not know, I am not from this area. I
relocated here about 10 years ago myself
from Las Vegas, Nevada. It was hands
down one of the best decisions I could
have ever made. And so you'll be really
getting that feedback from someone
that's not here originally. So, one of
the best pros is affordability and cost
of living. The cost of living here is
about 7% below the national average and
the housing is about 23% below the
national average. Our average home price
here in the Belton, Texas area is
somewhere between 275 and 280. That's
actually according to the Temple Belton
Board of Realtors um most recent June
2025 statistics. If you want more
information on the Temple, Belton, or
Central Texas statistics, you can head
on over to my T-B. That's my tbb.com
if you'd like to do some of that
research yourself. But in general, the
cost of living and affordability here is
really great, especially when you
compare it to places like Austin and
Waco, just north and south of us. So,
the number two pro, which is one of my
favorites, is outdoor parks and
recreation. We have a ton of parks and
things to do outside. Uh, as you can
see, we are at a beautiful park. This is
Temple Lake Park. Um, right on Belton
Lake. You can see behind me there are
people just swimming in the water, um,
barbecuing, hanging out. It's just shy
of 100° today. Perfect weather to be in
the lake. Light breeze, really awesome
and low expense thing to do. $5 entry at
the gate. Um, but we have a ton of other
parks here, too. You have Chalk Ridge
Falls, you have Miller Springs, you have
um Nolan Creek if you want to go hang
out at Nolan Creek in downtown Belton,
but a ton of options there if you're
looking for things to do outdoors. And
then, of course, here we are at Belton
Lake. There's going to be Belton Lake
and Stillhouse Lake. Um, both Still
House is going to be off of I14ish.
You're going to be closer to the
Colleen, Harker Heights, West Belton
area. Um, here and at Lake Belton,
you're going to be closer to Temple,
Belton, and Morgan's Point. Pro number
three, as I mentioned earlier, maybe
this is or isn't a pro for you. If
you're looking for that wild nightife,
Belton is probably not it. While we do
have a lot of things to do here, uh,
Belton is really putting a lot into its
infrastructure. Downtown Belton is
really growing, expanding. They are
remodeling a lot. You have a ton of
really great restaurants in the area.
And downtown Belton, we have Miller's
Barbecue. You have Nunia's Thai food.
That's my favorite. You have Water
Street Waffle Company. Um, I felt like
the area was really needing a awesome
breakfast spot here and that one is
fantastic. But if you actually want more
details in downtown Belton and what that
life looks like, I recently did a video
on downtown Belton, you should head on
over and take a look at that. But things
close at a relatively decent time, but
there's still plenty to do in terms of
dining, shopping, and of course, you're
only an hour north of Austin and 30
minutes south of Waco. You also have
Colleen Mall and shopping over in
Colleen. Downtown Belton also has some
really awesome boutiques, shopping,
Cochran Blair and Pots. We also have
festivals, farmers markets, just a lot
of really sweet small town charm feel
activities. Another pro is our school
district. Belton ISD is highly rated. If
of course if you head on over to
niche.com, nic.com,
Belton, Texas has an A minus rating
which is really great for this area.
your student toteer ratio is great and
there's just over 13,000 students
kindergarten um prek up to high school
and of course we're really known for our
higher education of Mary Harden Baylor
and surprisingly Temple Belton is a
major medical teaching facility and so
there is that education as well if you
want to consider that we're the largest
teaching facility from Austin all the
way to Dallas. Our last pro to highlight
is actually going to be location. You
are amazingly and centrally located. Um,
like I said, about an hour north of
Austin and 30 minutes south of Waco. But
what that really does for you is give
you access to some really popular spots.
And um, if you want to head down to
those places and have fun, you have the
great access and ability to do that. But
your cost of living is going to be
better here. You're going to get more
bang for your buck. you're going to get
more um you're going to get that lower
price per square foot as you move kind
of away from Austin. And so if you're
looking for more space, room to breathe,
you'd like a little more privacy,
that's going to be this is going to be a
benefit to you. You're about 20 minutes
east of Fort Hood, which is one of the
largest military installations in the
nation. And just really great
opportunity, especially with its
expansion and development. We're seeing
a lot of growth here very quickly, a lot
of new construction and a we're right up
that I35 corridor and uh I think this is
just a really great place to invest as
well if if that's something that you're
interested in. Belton, Texas is part of
Bell County, which is actually part of
the Colleen Temple metro area. Great
access to rivers, lakes, recreational
activities, and overall lower cost of
living. Just really makes this place a
wonderful place to be, especially if you
are looking for something a little
quieter and a little more peaceful than
that big city living. So, this may be
considered a pro or a con. Um sites like
Reddit are noting that because of its
the area's large military presence and
medical um growth that they that might
actually be limiting to some looking to
move here for work. I actually don't
think that's the case. I actually feel
that that's to me that's probably more
of a pro um just because there's so much
opportunity here. But that may be
something I guess just depending on what
your job field is. This was a huge
consideration for me were the weather
and bugs. So I came from Las Vegas where
it was more of a dry climate. Here is
much more humid, more muggy. So we have
very high hot summers but pretty
relatively mild winters. Snow is not
super common. We did have a snow
apocalypse of 2021. very rare, but
overall it's pretty hot here. You do get
the benefits of using these recreational
activities to enjoy the cool lake. Um,
and of course the springs while shore
are really awesome. We do have a lot of
bugs in the area. We have wasps,
spiders, big old tarantulas, which I
actually think are pretty cool. Um,
mosquitoes. I'm very sensitive to
mosquitoes. That one's a tough one for
me, but I make it through.
um scorpions
and rodents. There are quite a bit of
rodents as well as snakes, but I think
it's worth the trade-off. You'll have to
decide that for yourself. I think one of
the biggest cons to our area is actually
our property taxes, which is probably
going to apply to all of Texas, but
particularly here, your tax rate is
going to be somewhere between 1.6 six to
2.7%
just really depending on if you're
inside or outside of city limits and in
what area. That's really going to affect
your overall monthly payment. And so
while our homes are more affordable than
a lot of other places, that's definitely
something to consider. Um if you are
moving here, there are things like
exemptions that you can file to reduce
your taxable amount. Those are going to
be your homestead exemption, your over
65 exemption, and even exemptions for
disabled veterans. And then the last con
might be the small town charm if you're
actually looking for big city living. We
don't have the same amenities that
Austin, Texas does, if you're looking
for that nightife, but you're not far
from it. Belton, Texas thrives on small
town warmth, affordability, and access
to nature. Although it's not perfect, if
you value schools, community, and an
overall slower pace, it may just be the
perfect fit for you. If you have any
questions about relocating to Temple,
Belton, or any of the surrounding areas,
you can find all my contact information
below. I'd love to hear what you thought
about this video. Till next time, I'm
Andrea Dudik, realtor and associate
broker.